Mazal tov today's דף daf is מ״א mem alef 41, we pick
up on מ״א עמוד ב׳ mem amud bet near at the bottom
and it says four lines from the bottom.
So the משנה mishna had been talking
about the case of נזק nezik done by an ox, but we
had
appended
the and moved into questions about אפוטרופוס apitropus and whether when it
loses its identity as מועד, muad, becomes a מועד muad under an
אפוטרופוס, apitropus, but the last משנה mishna really the editors of the
גמרא gemara of the of the not the editors, the publishers of
the וילנא ש״ס, Vilna Shas, whatever appended to the end of the
last משנה mishna what should have been a new משנה mishna which
is focusing on כופר. kofer. And that's really where we've transitioned to.
So the the end of the last משנה mishna spoke about a
stadium ox and provoking it to gore and that you don't go
ahead and you don't stone the ox.
So the first question the גמרא gemara had was whether you could
use the ox on the מזבח, mizbe’ach, whether the fact that it
did an עבירה aveira makes it like a נרבע, nirva, it doesn't
matter that it was forced upon it or whether nevertheless the fact
that you don't stone it means that it does not have this
stigma associated to it and it does not become necessarily invalid for
the מזבח. mizbe’ach. It would be in a case where you wouldn't
actually stone it, like there would not be sufficient evidence, it would
be the testimony of the owners and so on, but nevertheless the
fact that it would have been deserving of stoning had you had
sufficient evidence, excuse me, it wouldn't have been deserving of stoning, but
the fact that it did gore right is that going to be
even if it was provoked is that sufficient to create this stigma
to of נעבד בעבירה ne’evad ba’aveira to invalidate it for the מזבח.
mizbe’ach. So the גמרא gemara did not resolve that. Now we get
on turn back to the issue actually about the stoning and the
כופר kofer and a more sort of central discussion. Let's take a
look. אמר מר: Amar Mar: נוגח משלם את הכופר רובע אינו משלם
את הכופר. nogei’ach meshaleim et hakofer rovei’a eino meshaleim et hakofer. Four
lines from the bottom on מ״א עמוד ב׳. mem amud bet. נוגח
משלם את הכופר רובע אינו משלם את הכופר. nogei’ach meshaleim et hakofer
rovei’a eino meshaleim et hakofer. So in that discussion of the what
animals are פסול pasul for the מזבח, mizbe’ach, one of them is
an animal that gored and the other is an animal that did
a act of bestiality, both of those if there were sufficient witnesses
would be stoned, but even if there's not sufficient testimony they're פסול
pasul for the מזבח. mizbe’ach. And it made a contrast between how
weighty they are because a נוגח nogei’ach will pay כופר, kofer, one
who gores pays כופר, kofer, and an animal who does bestiality does
not pay כופר. kofer. So that's the גמרא gemara is going to
say. So רובע אינו משלם את הכופר rovei’a eino meshaleim et hakofer
היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's
the case? אילימא דרבע וקטלה, Ilima de-rava ve-katla, if it basically in
the act of sex of bestiality in this act actually killed let's
say the woman that it was penetrating, so מאי לי קטלה בקרנא
מאי לי קטלה ברביע? ma li katla bekarna ma li katla birvia?
What difference does it make? It should be paying כופר. kofer. Why
do I care if it killed it with its horns or killed
it through an act of sex? It's an act of killing another
person and therefore there should be כופר, kofer, why not?
ואלא דרבע ולא קטלה, Ve-ela de-rava velo katla, it had this act
of sex without killing the woman. So האי דלא משלם כופר משום
דלא קטלה, hai dlo meshaleim kofer mishum dlo katla, so that's not
a weakness in the status of its being a רובע, rovei’a, that's
because it didn't actually murder somebody. Now if you ask me, that's
פשט pshat of the ברייתא. braisa. פשט pshat of the ברייתא braisa
is that in one case a רובע rovei’a is not just didn't
just do an עבירה, aveira, doesn't just get stoned, it took a
life, and the you know so that's makes it more weighty than
the case of רביע revia where it did an עבירה aveira but
it didn't take a life, you know in one case you're paying
כופר kofer because a life was taken. So that to me seems
exactly to be the point, but the גמרא gemara is saying is
oh that's not a legal difference between them, there's no כופר kofer
not because it's weaker but because it didn't take a life. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara said: אמר אביי לעולם דרבע ולא קטלה. Amar
Abaye l’olam de-rava velo katla. Fine, it it
it had sex and it didn't kill the woman. Okay, so then
of course you're not going to pay a כופר, kofer, no, but
דאמטויה לבי דינא וקטלוה, d'amtoyeh levei dina vekatluha, but because of the
act of bestiality it was stoned in בית דין. beis din. So
therefore מהו דתימא כמאן דקטלה דמי, mahu detaima keman dkatla dami, so
because I'm sorry, not it she was stoned because she participated in
an act of בית דין beis din an act of bestiality, she
was stoned, so therefore the act of רביע revia does take a
life, it takes a life by making the participant in it do
a do a transgression that's deserving of the death penalty, so maybe
therefore there should be a כופר kofer even though a human life
was was lost as a result of this act, כמאן דקטלה דמי
keman dkatla dami קא משמע לן kamashmalan that we don't say that.
Okay, which is a fascinating way of looking at it, but
תוספות tosafos of course asks the question that that in this case
presumably if the woman is getting stoned that means that the woman
or the woman's getting executed, I shouldn't say stone executed, then that
means that the woman was a willing and active participant in the
act, right? And if that's true, then the ox didn't gore her,
the ox didn't bring about her death, she brought about her own
death, right? She was a willing participant in it, so how do
you sort of say what was your
הוה אמינא havamina there? and then she just followed through, and you
could still sort of say that maybe it was the ox's fault.
Okay, but anyway, the question is I think better than the answer.
Okay, but that's אביי's Abaye position. One minute. רבא אמר לעולם דרבע
וקטלה. Rava amar le'olam de-reva ve-katla. No, no, no, it actually in
this act of sex, it actually was so violent and, you know,
I mean we are talking about a big bull, okay, that it
killed the woman. Okay, but so then why not pay כופר? kofer?
דקשיא לך מאי קטלה בקרנא מאי קטלה ברביעה? De-ka kashya lecha, mai
katla be-karna mai katla be-revi'ah? What do I care if it killed
it with its horns or it killed it with an act of
sex? No, it does make a difference. קרן כוונתו להזיק. האי כוונתו
להנאת עצמו. Keren kavanato lehazzik, hai kavanato la-hana'at atzmo. Here is a
great question. Is there the הלכה halakhah of כופר kofer by שן
ורגל shen ve-regel that killed someone? Okay, or is it only by
כוונתו להזיק? kavanato lehazzik? So this is an act of שן shen
that killed somebody, okay, so is that going to pay כופר? kofer?
קרן כוונתו להזיק Keren kavanato lehazzik. האי כוונתו להנאת עצמו. Hai kavanato
la-hana'at atzmo. במאי פליגי? Bemai palgi? What would be the debate? So
a parallel debate would be ברגל שדרסה גבי תינוק בחצר הניזק. be-regel
she-darsa gabei tinok be-chatzer hanizzak. So let's say in, let's say through
רגל, regel, an animal walked and stepped on an, on a tiny
baby, on an infant. Okay, notice it says בחצר הניזק, be-chatzer hanizzak,
because since we're dealing with שן ורגל, shen ve-regel, the presumption is
that the, that it would follow the parameters of paying for damages,
and there wouldn't be a liability in רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. Okay.
Now, of course, you know, one wonders about that, like if an
animal just, I don't know, attacked somebody to do this act of
sex, I don't know if that ever happens that an
animal forces itself on a human, but even if that were in
רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, it's not like, you know, animals have, it's
still כל המשתנה, kol hamishaneh, right? I mean it's not like people
can protect themselves against that, or the whole logic of רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim is you should be protecting yourself against these types of
things that happen in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, you know, the owner
has a right to have his animal do natural things in רשות
הרבים. reshut harabbim. So that might be true about leaving your tiny
infant baby right in the middle of the street. Like you don't
leave your infant baby in the middle of the street, cars are
going to run over it. Okay, so you know, but on the
other hand, like an animal attacking somebody and this act of sex,
whether that would also be limited to רשות הניזק reshut hanizzak is
an interesting question. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that fundamentally it follows
the same parameters. So would you have רגל regel of כופר kofer
if a person was killed, a baby was killed in רשות הניזק?
reshut hanizzak? Okay. ואביי משלם כופר לרבא לא משלם כופר. Ve-Abaye meshallem
kofer, le-Rava lo meshallem kofer. For אביי Abaye yes and for רבא
Rava no. What a great question, and surprisingly it doesn't come up
in the context of a משנה mishnah or of a ברייתא. braita.
It really just comes up in interpreting this משנה mishnah that's discussing
about the difference between כופר kofer about, about killing and
נוגח ורובע nogeach ve-rove'a for the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay. תניא כוותיה דרב.
Tanya kevattei de-Rav. סיטיא דאינו חייב מיתה וכשר לגבי מזבח משום שהוא
כאנוסה. Sitia de-eino chayyav mita ve-kasher legabei mizbe'ach mishum she-hu ke-anusah.
Not only is a סיטיא Sitia ox not חייב מיתה, chayyav mita,
it can even be used for the מזבח mizbe'ach because it's forced,
it did not choose to do it. So regardless of the case
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, we do have a great question of whether
there is כופר kofer by שן ורגל, shen ve-regel,
yes Dov.
Don't you find it at all problematic that the language we have
to use to discuss these cases almost sounds as if the animal
itself is like a בר דעת? bar da'at? What? It's almost as
if we're treating the animal...
Well yes, when it does come to stoning the animal, I mean
when it does come to stoning the animal, then what do you
call it, then it is like מיתת הבעלים כך
מיתת השור.
mitat
haba'alim kakh mitat hashor.
And we're going to see about that, actually some of that is
going to come up in a minute. Like let's say an animal
tried to gore, you know, an animal and it wound up killing
a person, you wouldn't make it a שור המועד shor hamu'ad because
it's מתכוון, mitkavein, you know, to kill one person and killed another
person. So yes, there is going to be a lot of that
parallel.
Now yes, Michael. So I'm just trying to understand, so you pay
כופר, kofer, at least according to the פסוקים, pesukim, only if it
was a מועד, mu'ad, right? And here it seems that you're paying
כופר kofer regardless, right? Because it's first if a שור shor kills
somebody then you kill the שור. shor. But then שור נגח הוא
מתמול שלשום והועד בבעליו ולא ישמרנו והמית איש או אשה השור יסקל
וגם בעליו יומת אם כופר יושת עליו. Shor nogeach hu mi-tmol shilshom
ve-hu'ad bi-ve'alav ve-lo yishmerennu ve-hemit ish o ishah ha-shor yisakkel ve-gam be'alav
yumat im kofer yushas alav. Well, so in the case of שן
ורגל, shen ve-regel, that's a good question. In the according to the
position that you pay כופר kofer by שן ורגל, shen ve-regel, would
you pay it immediately? The same way you pay נזק שלם nezek
shalem because it's already considered to be a מועד, mu'ad, you know,
I don't know, is an animal a מועד mu'ad to step on
little babies or whatever, to have sex with a person and kill
them in the process of having sex? You know, so I don't
know, but it's an interesting question. In the הוה אמינא hava amina
here that it would pay because when it was, you know, as,
you know, but if this was being categorized as a קרן, keren,
this act that maybe the woman was now going to be executed
in בית דין beis din and so on, you know, that was
sort of seen in the קרן keren lens and then we would
have to be talking about a scenario that it did it three
times, which you're right is obviously bizarre. Okay, the other interesting question
to ask and I want to sort of start framing this question
for you, which the גמרא's Gemara not addressed directly, is the relationship
between כופר Kofer and stoning the ox. For example, you don't pay
in the case of the stadium ox. Would you pay כופר? Kofer?
Okay, I mean also pay. You don't stone the ox in the
case of the stadium ox. Would you pay כופר, Kofer, right? And
you can certainly imagine that there could be more liability, like two
scenarios. One is that I sic my own ox, provoke my own
ox to gore somebody, you should say I should certainly pay כופר.
Kofer. The other is that ראובן Reuven provoked my ox to gore
שמעון, Shimon, right? And I'm much more of an אונס. Anus. Okay,
but the ox you don't stone. What'd it say about כופר? Kofer?
How about this case about
שן ורגל, Shein ve'Regel, right? Would the case of שן ורגל, Shein
ve'Regel, would you say that you would stone, you would stone, you
would—excuse me—you where what's the case? The גמרא's Gemara saying you,
you don't pay כופר, Kofer, right. Would you stone? That's the reverse.
In the case of a שן ורגל, Shein ve'Regel, according to the
way אביי Abaye reads it, one minute.
Right, so רבא Rava says you don't pay כופר Kofer by a
case of שן ורגל, Shein ve'Regel, right? So the animal sort of
did this act of sex or walked on this baby or whatever,
רבא Rava says you don't pay כופר. Kofer. So this animal killed
somebody. You're not going to pay כופר. Kofer. Would you stone the
animal or not stone the animal, right? So that I mean you
could always ask whenever you're discussing one of those two, the important
question to ask is what's the story with the other half of
it. So you don't stone the animal that was provoked. Okay, but
will the owners pay כופר? Kofer? You don't pay כופר Kofer according
to רבא Rava in a case of שן ורגל. Shein ve'Regel. Would
you stone the animal? There, it's more obvious I think in that
case that you wouldn't stone because what רבא's Rava saying is that
שן ורגל Shein ve'Regel are fundamentally a different category. And you could
certainly even say by logic you could even say all the more
so, right? If an animal did it without intention, if it wasn't
כוונתו להזיק, Kavanaso le'Hazik, it's less of an act of murder on
the animal's part and therefore less of a reason to stone it.
You might still want to pay כופר Kofer because a life was
taken, but it would seem in that case there's less of a
reason to stone it. Okay, but that I think is always the
question to be asking when you say something about one, what is
the story about the other half of it.
Yes, why it's so interesting that we do not treat the animal,
let's say a dog that I sic a dog on somebody, the
dog will kill the person.
Right. I mean it's so right, you remember well the גמרא Gemara
had the whole case
of, right, I mean the גמרא Gemara had the case if you
remember about the snake. And only if you assume that the poison
was in the fangs of the snake and the person directly put
it on the person. But if the poison had actually come out,
even though the person was completely physically manipulated it, it was considered
to be his—wasn't considered to be an act of direct murder.
Yeah, and even so that's the same as a bullet
coming out of a gun. Right, you would think, okay, but nevertheless
because somehow the snake is a separate live entity and has to,
you know, even though what would happen would be a direct result,
since it took a step and stage, right, that becomes a גרמא
Grama type of a case. Okay, anyway, but we're going to move
on. So the case of when it doesn't have כוונה להזיק, Kavanah
le'Hazik, it makes an enormous amount of sense to say that you
don't stone it, that you're not going to stone it and the
גמרא Gemara doesn't even sort of talking about that. But the question
remains, are will you still pay כופר? Kofer? And I would think
that that would be the general sort of logic that there be
could be cases where it's not wicked enough to be stoned, but
you might still pay כופר. Kofer. But again, like that would be
a question and we didn't address it by the stadium ox. Maybe
it's not stoned, will you pay כופר, Kofer, we don't know that
wasn't addressed. Let's look now at the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna
is now going to talk about the difference between the basic point
about מועד, Muad, that you need to be a מועד Muad to
be paying כופר. Kofer. It says it in the פסוקים, Pesukim, right?
ולא ישמרנו והמית איש או אשה השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת. Ve'lo
yishmurenu ve'heimis ish o ishah hashor yisakeil ve'gam ba'alav yumas. אם כופר
יושת עליו, Im kofer yushas alav, etc.
So it's clear that you only pay כופר Kofer after it—after it's
been warned and so on. So let's look at this משנה. Mishna.
שור שנגח את האדם ומת. Shor shenagach es adam vames. מועד משלם
כופר ותם פטור מן הכופר. Muad meshalem kofer vetam patur min hakofer.
מועד Muad pays כופר Kofer and a תם Tam is exempt. זה
וזה חייבים מיתה, Zeh va-zeh chayavim misa, but either one, as the
Torah says by the first time it does it, the Torah says
השור יסקל, Hashor yisakeil, right? סקול יסקל השור ולא יאכל את בשרו
ובעל השור נקי. Sekol yisakeil hashor velo yei'achel es besaro uva'al hashor
naki. Okay, וכן בבן וכן בבת. Ve-chein be-ven ve-chein be-vass. It also
is the same if it kills a child. Now, of course the
point is that's obvious, yes, but what the what's
the סוגיא מה. Sugya mah. I know, but what the משנה's Mishna
doing is it's working its way through the פסוקים, Pesukim, right? The
פסוקים Pesukim basically have that. They say או בן יגח או בת
יגח כמשפט הזה יעשה לו. O ven yigach o vass yigach kamishpat
hazeh yei'aseh lo. And does anybody know what the next פסוק Pasuk
is? אם עבד יגח השור,
Im
eved yigach hashor, right?
So it's או בן יגח או בת יגח, O ven yigach o
vass yigach, okay, and then it says אם עבד יגח השור Im
eved yigach hashor which is the next line of the משנה. Mishna.
So the משנה Mishna is working through.
So the משנה Mishnah is working its way through the פסוקים. pesukim.
Okay. So, נגח עבד או אמה נותן שלושים סלעים, nagach eved o
amah noten shloshim sla'im, you pay thirty שקל, shekel, בין שהוא יפה
מאה מנה, bein shehu yafeh me'ah maneh, בין שאינו יפה אלא דינר
אחד. bein she'eino yafeh ela dinar echad. Whether it's worth a hundred
מנה, maneh, which is a huge amount, or whether it's only worth
one דינר, dinar, it's always the the slave, how much would the
slave go in the slave market? You always pay thirty שקל, shekel,
so as opposed to כופר, kofer, which as we've seen before is
a debate about how much either the owner of the ox or
the killed person would would go in the slave market, what their
value would be, but it's based on the slave market and it's
based on the particular person, by the the ironically by the slave
itself, it's not based either by the slave market and it's not
based by his going price, it's based by a fixed amount of
thirty שקל. shekel. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
וכי מאחר דמתם קטלינן ליה מועד היכי משכחת ליה. vechi me'achar demitam
katlinan lei mu'ad heichi mashkachat lei.
If once you're going to kill the ox as a תם, tam,
if you actually did what the תורה Torah said, you stoned the
ox the first time, how does it ever live long enough to
be a מועד? mu'ad?
Oh, maybe he gored an ox three times.
Alright, let's take a look. Good. Let's take a look. אמר רב
רבא הכא במאי עסקינן כשעמדו לשלושה בני אדם. amar rav rabba hacha
bemai askinan she'amdu lishlosha bnei adam. That basically you saw the way
רש"י Rashi describes it is, it was running after people and it
almost would have killed them except they made a last minute escape,
but you see that it has in it the desire and the
violence and the and the you know the nature to go and
to try to kill people. Of course the funny thing is maybe
it's never it's not smart enough to actually succeed in doing it.
So that doesn't actually mean that it's going to be able to
kill people, okay, and maybe it just wanted to gore them without
killing them. How do you know it would have actually you know
gone through and totally killed them? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says רב
אשי אמר אומדנא לאו כלום הוא. rav ashi amar umdna lav klum
hu. That doesn't count for anything, why just because you assess it
would have had it gored them. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, ela hacha
bemai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שסיכן לשלושה בני אדם.
kegon shesiken lishlosha bnei adam. It it critically injured three people, okay,
and because it critically injured you couldn't kill it yet, right, because
because the person hadn't died, so you can't actually execute the שור
shor before the person is dead, but you can actually warn the
owner and say, your ox has you know goes out and fatally
wounds people, you have to watch it. So that's good enough to
warn the owner and to identify that it has that ability to
actually and actually it acts on fatally wounding people. So that's enough
to make it a שור המועד shor hamu'ad and then if it
actually רש"י Rashi would say the people would actually have to die
before you pay כופר, kofer, but it would be good enough for
to make it into a שור המועד shor hamu'ad and for you
to be warned, but presumably until they actually died it would not
fully have that status to be a שור המועד shor hamu'ad for
you to pay כופר, kofer, although I don't know if that's clear
in the גמרא. Gemara. רש"י Rashi says שסיכן ג' בני אדם, shesiken
gimmel bnei adam, he says לכך לא נסקל בשם הראשון וכשנגח שלישי
מתו כולם הילכך משלם עליו את הכופר. l'kach lo niscal b'shem harishon
u'kshenagach shlishi metu kulam hilchach meshalem alav et hakofer. So I'm not
exactly sure why you have to say מתו כולם, metu kulam, why
don't you just say the last guy died? Okay, but
but you know if that was good enough to make it into
a מועד mu'ad why do they all have to die before you
pay the last כופר? kofer? Anyway, the other interesting thing I should
mention by the way and I've been sort of hiding this from
you is because רש"י Rashi consistently assumes that the full payment of
a מועד mu'ad or the payment of a כופר kofer comes at
the third goring. Okay, that is not פשט pshat of all the
סוגיות, sugyot, as תוספות Tosafot makes clear פשט pshat of all the
סוגיות sugyot is, it did it three times, the first three times
it was a תם, tam, so that by the fourth time it'll
be a מועד, mu'ad, right, and that's like the simple sense of
the גמרא. Gemara. Because it gored three people and fatally injured them,
now it is a מועד mu'ad for the fourth person it will
gore. Right, that's the simple read of all this all these גמרות.
gemarot. רש"י Rashi always reads it that it's a מועד mu'ad that
the third one it pays full, the third one it pays כופר.
kofer. Anyway, that's the case of that's that's whose answer was that?
רב אשי's Rav Ashi answer. וזביד אמר, Vezevid amar, Rav Zevid says
כגון שהרג שלושה בהמות. kegon sheharag shlosha behemot. Like Michael said it
killed three בהמות. behemot. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
ומועד לבהמה הוי מועד לאדם? umu'ad livehema havay mu'ad l'adam? You've injured
something as habitual to kill a בהמה, behema, that makes it a
מועד mu'ad for killing people? Now, you might remember that there was
a debate before of רב זביד Rav Zevid and who was it
רב אשי Rav Ashi whether וימועד צנא, v'imu'ad tzana, you know,
or ואינו מועד צנא. v'eino mu'ad tzana. And רב זביד's Rav Zevid
read was וימועד v'imu'ad meaning רב זביד Rav Zevid read it that
yes, we assume that based at least based on the things that
it's goring, that we do not limit it to the what we
concretely saw. We assume once it became a מועד mu'ad in the
standard case, unless it's been obvious that it's not goring certain types
of people or animals, but without that evidence we assume that it's
going to be a מועד mu'ad to gore everything whether and even
if it gored animal it will be a מועד mu'ad to gore
אדם. adam. That was רב זביד, Rav Zevid, רב זביד Rav Zevid
is completely consistent. But the גמרא Gemara here like is just the
סתמא דגמרא stama d'gemara thinks that's absurd. Of course you don't go
from one to the other, which is again proof for the רי"ף's
Rif position that we rule like I think it was רב פפא
Rav Pappa who was it before? Anyway, we rule like ואינו מועד
צנא. v'eino mu'ad tzana. That exactly that is the presumption of all
these גמרות gemarot that you do not generally abstract it. You read
it, you interpret the העדאה, ha'adaah, you interpret it becoming a מועד
muad in the narrowest way possible that fits the evidence of what
it has done. Okay, so that's what—so the גמרא Gemara rejects רב
זביד's Rav Zevid read. You can't go from בהמה behema to אדם,
adam, no, if it killed בהמה, behema, it's only a מועד muad
for a בהמה. behema. אלא אמר רב שימי, Ella amar Rav Shimi,
so רב שימי Rav Shimi says, כגון שהרג שלושה עובדי כוכבים. kegon
she'harag shelosha ovdei kochavim. Now actually the original גרסא girsa was גוים,
goyim, but you know, as I said, we edit out—we censor all
those things out. Okay, oh well, it killed non-Jews, so because the
reason it's censored out is because the obvious point is you don't
stone an ox for goring non-Jews, you only stone an ox for
goring Jews. But clearly though it has a propensity for killing people,
so it becomes
a
מועד. muad. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומועד לעובדי כוכבים, מועד לגוים,
הוי מועד לישראל? u'muad le'ovdei kochavim, muad le'goyim, havei muad le'Yisrael? What?
You just think because of one it'll be a מועד muad for
the other? Now again, this begins to indicate—remember the גמרא Gemara in
the end had this case about it doing on alternating days and
doing on the 15th of אותו? oto? Well, suppose there was a
reason. Maybe we raised the question after when we did that earlier
גמרא, Gemara, when you limit it to the—to the circumstances of the
goring, does there have to be a logic behind it, or is
it just a formal process? And if this is the only thing
it did, then in a formal way that's the only identity it
can have as a מועד. muad. So the most obvious case where
we were being by the end of that סוגיא sugya a while
ago, a week ago or so, completely formalist was the idea that
if it gored on the 15th of each month, or the 15th,
the 16th, and the 17th, that it established that type of a
pattern. I mean, I don't know, maybe you could say it's being
affected by the moon or something. Okay, but it seemed like the
גמרא Gemara was being highly formalistic, and that could be the same
point here. Like, who needs to give a reason? If it's only
killed non-Jews, then that would only be a מועד muad for killing
non-Jews. I don't know, let's say it only killed people so far
right now, it's only killed people between the age between 20 and
24. Would you say—I'm serious, like, how far, how narrow do you
do just by—because of the circumstances of what it actually did these
three times? It could be, however, the גמרא Gemara assumes that there
is a reason. The גמרא Gemara often says an idea like that's,
you know,
that—that like you know, this sense maybe that Jews have special protection,
like a little bit more, like you know, like special divine protection.
So maybe just cause it was able to kill non-Jews, you know,
I don't know if history bears out the fact that we have
been more protected from—from onslaught and injury or whatever. But anyway, what?
Maybe from an ox and we have, right, it's only from oppression
from non-Jews that we haven't, but from oxen we've been even more
protected.
Differences in dress—oh
oh okay, maybe they dress in a different way. That's a good
point. Although in the time—there's a lot of evidence that in the
time of the גמרא Gemara there was no difference in dress. So
anyway, okay, not even a כיפה. kippah. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: כגון שהרג שלושה עובדי כוכבים. kegon she'harag shelosha
ovdei kochavim. ומועד לעובדי כוכבים הוי מועד לישראל? u'muad le'ovdei kochavim havei
muad le'Yisrael? What? That wouldn't make it a מועד muad for killing
Jews. אלא אמר ריש לקיש, Ella amar Resh Lakish, כגון שהרג שלושה
בני אדם טרפה. kegon she'harag shelosha benei adam tereifa. It's killed three
people that were a טרפה, tereifa, and here you see that when
we only stone the ox we do treat it as how would
we treat a case of if a human being murdered. So for
a human being who commits murder, if the victim is a טרפה,
tereifa, has an internal injury that'll die—he'll die within a year, then
that is not considered to be an act of—that you execute somebody
for. Now I want to point out it's not just about life
expectancy. If somebody is—we actually פוסקין pasken like חיי שעה, chayei sha'ah,
even if somebody is basically like, you know, on—dying of cancer and
has just minutes left to live and somebody were to kill him,
that would actually be murder and you would execute the
person. Okay, because—but it's specifically the status of a טרפה—or tereifa maybe
cancer isn't a good issue because maybe that would sort of be—I
don't know exactly what that does to be inside—but someone is dying
of old age, let's say. Whereas a טרפה, tereifa, something based on
a specific phenomenon of an internal injury, that halachically gives a person
a different status. But the point is that it's not just a
question—it's not a גוסס, goses, it's not just a question of life
expectancy. Okay, so we say that normally by the case of murder
that a person would not be executed if they kill a טרפה.
tereifa. So that's how the גמרא Gemara has this answer. Oh, so
you won't execute the שור shor either, but it'll be a מועד
muad because clearly it killed people. So the גמרא Gemara says,
כגון שהרג שלושה בני אדם טרפה. kegon she'harag shelosha benei adam tereifa.
So the גמרא Gemara rejects that too. ומועד לטרפה הוי מועד לשלם?
u'muad le'tereifa havei muad le'shalem? What, just cause it's a מועד muad
for a טרפה tereifa is it a מועד muad for a שלם?
shalem? Now again, the גמרא Gemara might think, you know, maybe a
טרפה tereifa is—can't defend himself as well. Maybe, you know, sends off
messages to the animals that pick up on that scent that this
person's about to die, you know, the same way like the ravens
start to circle or whatever. You know, so who knows what it
is? Maybe he attracts goring animals the way a שלם shalem would
not. Okay, so anyway, all right, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא אמר רב פפא דקטל וערק לאגמא דקטל וערק לאגמא. Ella amar
Rav Pappa de'katal ve'arak le'agma de'katal ve'arak le'agma. Let's not try to
get a fancy—a case about that you were going to transfer from
one type of a goring to another because you seem to be
highly formalistic here and not allow us to be abstracting at all.
So fine, he did do three gorings and he should have been
stoned by the first one, but every time בית דין Beis Din
wasn't able to capture him. I mean, he was a pretty wild
ox. So. He ran away, remember we had the swamp the other
day where you're hiding your ox? He ran away to the swamp,
בית דין Beis Din isn't able to capture him, but they warned
the owner and they say, you'd better watch that ox, you know,
we're going to try to kill it if we get it into
our hands, but you'd better watch it, and you know, and so
on, and then he went and he gored again and that happens
three times. בית דין Beis Din was not able to capture it
in order to stone it, and therefore, but the owner was warned.
Now the irony is or the interesting thing is when it says
our ox that ran away is that, you know, following this idea
that you treat the ox like a person who committed murder is
that you basically, you know, have to have the accepting you have
to have the court case in the presence of the ox. The
ox has got to be. Yeah. So the ox actually had to
have been captured, right, although not necessarily. No, no, maybe the point
is you didn't have the court case to begin with, right? You
meaning you saw that it accepted. Well, no, because you have to
accept the testimony that it killed. That would be an interesting question.
If the ox has run away and we can't hold the court
case to stone it because the ox isn't present, so we can't
take the testimony of the witnesses that it's killed for the purpose
of basically executing the ox, can you still accept the testimony of
the witnesses for the purpose of warning the owner? So that might
be. Okay. So, you know, that might be.
So because because the ox did not testify in its own.
Exactly. Okay. So anyway, so alright, so the ox isn't around and
it's possible to read this that you could even accept the witnesses
even not in the presence of the ox, but the ox isn't
around so you're not able to stone the ox. Okay. רב אחא
בריה דרב איקא אמר כגון שהוזמו זוממי זוממין. Rav Acha brei de-Rav
Ika amar kegon she-huzmu zommei zomemin. Okay. So the people who
are מזמן mezamen the עדים edim and turn them into זוממין, zomemin,
they themselves became עדים זוממין. edim zomemin. What does that mean? It
means
two witnesses came, pair one of witnesses came and said your ox
gored, you know, your ox gored somebody and we're going to put
it to and they accepted the testimony in court so they're going
to put it to death. And then from and then before they
did that, a group number of witnesses number two said, oh, you
can't you don't know that. עמנו היית באותו היום. Immanu hayisa b'oso
hayom. You were with us on that day. You're lying. Okay, you're
lying, throw out the whole court case. Okay. Then that happened a
second time. Witnesses came again and said your ox gored, we have
to stone your ox, and group number two said you can't say
that. You were with us. Okay, throw it out. Happened a third
time. Okay. Then what happened was was that the group number two
that had been undermining, consistently undermining the testimony of group number one,
then group number two, then let's say, then a group number three
came and said, how could you be undermining the testimony of group
number one? You were with us on all those days. So what
happens at that stage? You throw out group number two and you
resuscitate group number one's testimony. Now it becomes valid. Okay. And now
it turns out that the owner was warned all three times, right,
because each time the testimony of group number one had been accepted
and it turns out that the ox genuinely had gored. Okay, now
of course the owner could say, how did I know? I didn't
know if it's gored or not. I trusted the group number two.
I didn't take the warning of group number one seriously because it
turned out that because I was believing group number two that group
number one was lying. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
הניחא אי ליועדי תורא בעינן. Hani-cha i-leyudei tora ba-inan. So the גמרא
Gemara says that if the whole purpose is to prove that the
ox has been warned, the ox has been testified against and the
ox is בחזקת מועד שפירא, be-chezkas mu-ad she-pira, then you know by
the end that all three testimonies originally were correct and that he
had done it three times. אלא ליועדי גברא בעינן, Ella i-leyudei gavra
ba-inan, but if the person needs to be warned and take the
warning seriously and then violate it three times, so מימר אמר ליה,
meimar amar lei, he could say, אלא לא הוה ידענא, A-lo hovei
yedina, I didn't know that my ox was goring, I trusted you
know group number two that invalidated the testimony. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, כגון דאמרי, kegon de-amri, no, because what group number one
said was, כל אימת דקטל תורא גבאי הוי קאי. kol eimas de-katil
tora gabei havai kai.
Every time your ox gored you were there. So group number one
was constantly testifying and saying your ox gored and you were there.
So when it turned out retroactively that group number one was telling
the truth, he can't, you know, you knew they were telling the
truth. It was very nice that there was other witnesses that were
saying they were lying, but you were warned and even after group
number two, the זוממין zomemin came, you knew that the group number
two was lying. So that warning still should have counted as a
good warning for you and they are testifying that you were present
so clearly you should have taken that seriously.
What's the difference between the two עדויות? eduyos? One is that we
were מעיד me'id that what, that the
ox...
Group number one says that they are testifying that your ox gored,
okay, your ox gored, okay, that's what they're testifying and they're saying
that you the owner was there and you saw it gore, okay,
that's what they're testifying, there's the
dead. Okay, so
and then that happens three times. Okay, so he can say, but
when but then it turns out that group number three says you're
lying and then that makes this okay, okay. So basically what we're
saying is every single time group number one warned you, you knew
they were telling the truth, okay, you you they said you were
there, now we believe them in their original testimony that you were
there. So now we believe that every time they testified you knew
they were telling the truth and you were properly warned. And you
can't say well once they were proven liars in בית דין Beis
Din I didn't have to pay attention to them. You knew group
number two was lying all along. That warning was still good for
you.
I'm just asking איהי אודי תורי איהי אודי גברא. Iyhee odei tori
iyhee odei gavra. In other words, is this what?
Oh because because if because if because even if you weren't around,
right, even if they weren't testifying that you were around, if the
whole point of the witnesses is to just prove that the ox
is habitual, then he can't say well I didn't know. Who cares
if you knew they were telling the truth? Now you know that
your ox has killed three times, okay? They were witnesses, right? Which
by the way, if you're saying ידיעה תורי, yedia tori, that's the
easiest answer. The easiest answer is is that one group of witnesses
comes to בית דין Beis Din and says your ox has gored
three times. Okay, you still need to say how did it get
away after that to gore a fourth time? But anyway, but you
know, but but that's the point, you would not need the person
to be warned each time and then it gores, you just need
to know at the end of the day it gored three times.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבינא
אמר במכירין את בעל השור ואין מכירין את השור.
Ravina amar
bemakirin es baal hashor veein makirin es hashor. So they say, look,
we know one of your oxen gored and killed somebody, we don't
know which ox. Okay, so we can't stone it. But now but
then what happens is that then by the third time they say
actually oh now we recognize or the fourth time whatever, now we
know that it's been this ox all along, okay? So by the
end they recognize it but each time you received warning but they
couldn't stone the ox because they didn't recognize which ox it was
until the last time when they then they recognized that that was
the ox that had been doing it all along. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, מאי הוה ליה למעבד? Mai hava lei
lemevad? But if you didn't know which ox it was and you
couldn't gore it, then I didn't know which ox it was to
stop it from goring, so what was I supposed to do? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, משום דאמרי ליה תורא נגחא אית לך
בבקרא. Mishum deamri lei tora nagcha is lach bevikra. Okay, because they
could say look, you do have a goring ox in amongst your
cattle, so איבעי לך לנטורי כולי בקרא. Ibayi lach linterei kulei bakra.
Your responsibility now is to watch all of your cattle. That's enough
to obligate you that one ox is a murderous ox, to obligate
you to watch all of them. You can't say ah I have
no responsibility because I don't know which one. Okay, so that was
a case where we can't stone the ox, but by the by
the end we realize it's been the same ox all along and
we identify it so we can stone the ox and make you
pay כופר. kofer. All right, so a lot of very interesting scenarios
that the גמרא Gemara draws. Let's take a look. Okay, וזה וזה
חייבין מיתה. Veze veze chayavin misa. Okay, so so the כופר kofer
is only by the third or fourth time, and but in already
it's חייב מיתה chayav misa from the first time.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, ממשמע שנאמר סקול יסקל השור, Mimmashma sheneemar sakol
yisakel hashor, once it says that you shall stone the ox, right
this is by the first time, איני יודע שנבלה היא, Eini yodea
sheneveila hie, then it's obviously a נבלה, neveila, it's an animal that
hasn't been properly slaughtered. ונבלה אסורה באכילה, Veneveila asura bachila, and you
can't eat it and you can't eat it. So מה תלמוד לומר
לא יאכל את בשרו? Ma talmud lomar lo yeachel es besaro? Why
does it say stone it and don't eat the meat? Of course
you don't eat the meat, it's a נבלה, neveila, just say stone
it. So the גמרא Gemara says מה תלמוד לומר? Ma talmud lomar?
מגיד לך הכתוב שאם שחטו לאחר שנגמר דינו, Magid lecha hakatuv sheim
shechato leachar shenigmar dino, once it's in a status that it deserves
to be stoned, did I skip a line? Okay, once it's in
a status that it deserves to be stoned, okay, סקול יסקל, sakol
yisakel, that's the status, then already לא יאכל את בשרו, lo yeachel
es besaro, then it becomes forbidden to be eaten. So even if
you succeeded in שחט-ing shecht it and not carrying out the judgment,
once the judgment has been passed, it has a status of שור
הנסקל shor haniskal and the meat is forbidden even if you שחט
shecht it. Okay, לאחר שנגמר דינו אסור באכילה. Leachar shenigmar dino asur
bachila. אין לי אלא באכילה, Ein li ela bachila, so that's one
thing you learn from לא יאכל את בשרו. lo yeachel es besaro.
אין לי אלא באכילה, Ein li ela bachila, now I only know
you can't eat the meat. בהנאה מניין, Behanaah minayin, how do I
know you can't get any benefit from it? תלמוד לומר ובעל השור
נקי. Talmud lomar ubaal hashor naki.
The owner of the ox is clean. Now the simple sense of
that פסוק pasuk is
it's in contrast to וגם בעליו יומת, vegam baalav yummas, right? So
פסוק pasuk says what it says, או נודע כי שור נגח הוא.
O noda ki shor nagach hu. או נודע כי שור נגח הוא.
O noda ki shor nagach hu. Okay, so this is a case
of מועד. muad. Okay, so מועד muad you deserve death, וגם בעליו
יומת vegam baalav yummas means you deserve death. אם כופר יושת עליו,
Im kofer yushas alav, but you can buy your buy back your
life by paying some type of a monetary atonement payment. The simple
sense of the פסוק pasuk by the way is that if you
don't have the money to pay כופר kofer we will kill you.
Okay, that's fine. Let's sound the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* but even if
you say it means you deserve death but you have an but
instead of death you're going to get כפר *kofer*. But the first
time it says כי יגח שור איש *ki yigach shor ish* right?
What is it? No, no, no, not את et,
רעהו *et
re'ehu*. What is it anyway?
מה? *mah?* מה?
*mah?* Tell me, just tell me.
וכי יגח שור את et איש *veki yigach shor et ish*.
Oh וכי יגח שור את et? איש *veki yigach shor et ish*
או את et, אשה ומת *o et isha vamet*, את et, איש
*et ish* או את et אשה ומת *o et isha vamet*, סקול
יסקל sakol yissakel *sakol yisakel* right השור *hashor* ולא יאכל *velo yeachel*
ולא יאכל את בשרו
et besaro, *velo yeachel et
besaro* right ובעל השור נקי U'ba'al hashor naki. *uba'al
hashor naki*. So so this ובעל השור נקי U'ba'al hashor naki. *uba'al
hashor naki* is here השור יסקל *hashor yisakel* which echoes סקול יסקל
*sakol yisakel*, but here it's ובעל השור נקי U'ba'al hashor naki *uba'al
hashor naki* and it's גם בעליו יומת *gam bealav yummat*. So obviously
the פשט pshat *pshat* of the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* is, hey,
it did it the first one or two times or whatever, you
can't be blamed for that, you don't have any real you know
guilt, you're certainly not deserving of death, we just gotta kill your
ox. Okay, so that's פשט *pshat*. But the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is
going to read ובעל השור נקי U'ba'al hashor naki, *uba'al hashor naki*
in a very different way. Let's take a look. Okay, מאי
*mai* where were we? Okay. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan *tanu rabbanan* ובעל
השור נקי naki, *uba'al hashor naki*. אין לי אלא באכילה *ein li
ela ba'achilah*. I only know you can't eat it. בהנאה behanaah, מניין
*bahan'ah minayin*? How do I know you can't get הנאה hanaah. *han'ah*?
תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar* ובעל השור נקי naki *uba'al hashor naki*. You're
clean. מאי משמע *mai mashma*? Where do you get that from that
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? שמעון בן זומא אומר omer *shimon ben zoma omer*
כאדם שאומר לחברו *keadam sheomer lechavero* יצא איש פלוני נקי naki מנכסיו
*yatza ish ploni naki mikhasav*. This person was cleaned out of his
out of his property ואין לו בו הנאה hanaah. כלום *veein lo
bo hana'ah klum* and he has no benefit left of him. He,
you know, he's left completely with nothing, he's been cleaned out. So
so those idioms don't go away. All right, anyway so ובעל השור
נקי *uba'al hashor naki* means you get cleaned out from your ownership
of the ox, you can't get any benefit. וממאי דלא יאכל את
בשרו et besaro להיכא דשחטו לאחר שנגמר דינו דאסור באכילה *u'mimai delo
yeachel et besaro lehekha deshacheto le'achar shenigmar dino de'asur ba'achilah*? So that's
what we know. You don't get benefit and the status begins once
the it's been it's been judged as a שור נסקל *shor nishkal*
even before it's been stoned. וממאי דלא יאכל את בשרו et besaro?
להיכא דשחטו לאחר שנגמר דינו *u'mimai delo yeachel et besaro lehekha deshacheto
le'achar shenigmar dino*? How do you know לא יאכל את בשרו lo
yeachel et besaro *lo yeachel et besaro* is telling you that it's
referring to a case when it was שחט shachat *shechted* after the
judgment has been passed, that you can't you can't derive any benefit
or eat it already at that stage? אימא *eima*, why don't I
say להיכא דשחטו לאחר שנגמר דינו שרי באכילה *lehekha deshacheto le'achar shenigmar
dino shari ba'achilah*? Maybe if you succeeded in שחט shachat *shechting* it,
maybe it would be
permissible because you did not execute it and it's only gets its
status when it's actually executed. Who? והאי לא יאכל את בשרו lo
yeachel et besaro *vehai lo yeachel et besaro*? So why do I
need לא יאכל את בשרו lo yeachel et besaro *lo yeachel et
besaro*? If it's already stoned and executed, it's a נבלה *nevelah*. להיכא
דסקלי מסקל *lehekha desakli miskal* that would be a case that it
was executed, it was stoned דאסור בהנאה *de'asur bahana'ah*. And maybe what
לא יאכל את בשרו lo yeachel et besaro *lo yeachel et besaro*,
maybe ובעל השור נקי *uba'al hashor naki* is not telling you that
you can't get הנאה hanaah, *han'ah*. That will tell you something else,
we'll see what in a minute. And maybe לא יאכל lo yeachel,
את בשרו et besaro *lo yeachel et besaro*, the point of that,
the whole status would only be after it's stoned. So why does
it have to say don't eat? You already can't eat it, it's
a נבלה *nevelah*. לא יאכל lo yeachel *lo yeachel* tells you don't
get הנאה hanaah. *han'ah*. כרבי אבהו *kerabbi abbahu*, like רבי Rebbi, אבהו
*rabbi abbahu*. דאמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי אלעזר *damar rabbi abbahu amar
rabbi elazar* כל מקום שנאמר *kol makom shene'emar* לא יאכל lo yeachel
*lo yeachel*, לא יאכל lo yeachel. *lo yokhal*, לא lo, תאכל *lo
tokhal*, לא תאכלו *lo tokhlu*, אחד איסור אכילה issur achilah, ואחד איסור
הנאה issur hanaah. במשמע *echad issur achilah ve'echad issur han'ah bamashma*. Whenever
it says don't eat, don't eat includes don't get benefit, עד *ad*,
unless the תורה Torah *torah* explicitly tells you you're allowed to get
benefit שיפרט לך הכתוב כדרך שפרט לך בנבלה *sheyafrit lekha hakatuv kederekh
sheperat lekha benevelah*. Like it tells you by a נבלה *nevelah*. What
does it say by a נבלה *nevelah*? It says לא תאכלו כל
נבלה לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה ואכלה או מכור לנכרי *lo tokhlu khol
nevelah lager asher bisharekha titnenah va'akhalah o makhor lenokhri*. Don't eat a
נבלה *nevelah*, give it to the sojourner or sell it to the
foreigner. Which means that why does the תורה Torah *torah* have to
tell me give it to the sojourner or sell it to the
foreigner? Just tell me don't eat it. I can figure out that
I can go ahead and I'm not going to throw it out,
I'll make some money off of it, I'll give it away, I'll
sell it or whatever. Okay, so the fact the תורה Torah *torah*
had to tell me that I can give it or sell it
shows me by default I should assume when it says don't eat,
it means don't get benefit. Okay, that's the position of רבי אבהו
*rabbi abbahu*. Since the תורה Torah *torah* had to tell you there
you can get benefit, you can learn from this that whenever it
says don't eat, it means don't get benefit unless it explicitly tells
you it's permissible. לגר בנתינה ולנכרי במכירה *lager binetinah velanokhri bimkhirah*, to
the stranger as a gift, to the foreigner as a sale. אמרי
Amri, *amri*, anyway so maybe לא יאכל lo yeachel את בשרו et
besaro *lo yeachel et besaro* just means don't get הנאה hanaah *han'ah*.
And we're not but still we're talking that you stoned it. No,
אמרי *amri*, no you could say הני מילי להיכא דנפיק ליה איסור
אכילה achilah ואיסור הנאה מקרא דלא יאכל *hani milei lehekha denafik leh
issur achilah ve'issur han'ah mikra delo yeachel*. If לא יאכל lo yeachel
*lo yeachel* is coming to tell you don't eat, then it includes
don't get benefit. So the תורה Torah *torah* will say לא יאכל
lo yeachel, *lo yokhal*, לא יאכל *lo yeachel* to mean don't eat
and don't get benefit. אבל הכא דאכילה מסקול יסקל נפקא *aval hakha
de'achilah missakol yisakel nafka*, but here if I already know that you
can't eat it because it's been stoned and it's a נבלה *nevelah*,
so the only thing, the only point of the תורה Torah *torah*
now saying something new is just to tell me don't get הנאה
*han'ah*. If that's true, האי לא יאכל את בשרו et besaro, איסור
הנאה issur hanaah. הוא *hai lo yeachel et besaro issur hana'ah hu*.
So the only point of לא יאכל *lo yeachel* is not to
tell me both אכילה *achilah* and הנאה *han'ah*. Here it's just to
tell me הנאה *han'ah*. So if that's true, נכתב רחמנא לא יהנה
*nikhtav rachmana lo yehane*. So then just say what you mean to
say. Say don't get benefit. Okay, if it has to tell me
don't eat, and it wants to incorporate don't get benefit, fine. But
here I already know you can't eat it. So if the only
point now is to say don't get benefit, just say that, say
what you're trying to say. אינמי, לא יאכל, or look, maybe it
will say לא יאכל and that will just cover both. But even
if that's true, את בשרו, et besaro, למה לי? lama li? Why
does it have to say the flesh, the meat? Just tell me
don't get benefit. Let's say לא יאכל means eating or benefit. What
is את et, בשרו besaro, coming to tell me?
So he has the point, the passive verb, לא יאכל.
Well, that's also true, but we're not getting into that, but that
is relevant in the general issue of whether it means הנאה. But
the point here is why does it say את et בשרו? besaro.
דאף אגב—so deaf agav this is where I know that it's telling
me even after, even if you שחטת shachtat it. Because את בשרו
is telling me the following: דאף אגב דעבדיה כעין בשר, deaf agav
deavdia k'ein basar,
you made it like meat. Meaning you did not, you know, you
actually בשר, basar, actually they have a word for it, like say
beef, right? You know, it's like, it's like,
you know, the, I remember this whole thing about like what, you
know, about like when certain like animals, like the words they use
for them in a culinary context. You know, so beef doesn't mean,
you know, it clearly means meat that you're going to be eating,
right? So that's what the גמרא Gemara is sort of saying like
here, that לא יאכל את בשרו means even though you made it
into beef, you שחטת shachtat it, it's still אסור, assur, it's still
a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. Okay, דשחטיה deshachtei אסור. assur. Okay, so
even though you שחטת shachtat it and made it like בשר. basar.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying לא יאכל את בשרו is coming
to tell me, this tells me it's a, this tells me it's
a נבילה neveilah if you actually stoned it. לא יאכל את בשרו
is telling me even if you שחטת shachtat it, once it had
the judgment passed, even if you made it into beef and you
שחטת shachtat it, it still is an, it still can't be eaten.
And then this tells me not only can it not be eaten,
you also can't even derive benefit from it. Okay, מתקיף לה מר
זוטרא. matkif la Mar Zutra. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra asks, אימא הני
מילי, eima hanei milei, let me say that's true that you cannot,
when you made it like beef, you can't get benefit even if
you didn't stone it, היכא דבדק צור ושחט בה, heicha de'badak tzur
v'shachat bah, if you שחטת shachtat it with a nice sharp flint.
You checked the flint to make sure it had no nicks, it
was a כשר שחיטה kasher shechitah knife, and you used a rock
to do a שחיטה. shechitah. So you did a שחיטה shechitah that
was like stoning it with a, you know, like stoning, okay? So
maybe that would be the best way to have it with a
סקול יסקל and it was a type of a בשר, basar, because
the שחט shechted it with a rock was a type of a
סקילה. sekilah.
Maybe that's the case where you can't get, where it applies even
if it wasn't stoned. דעבדיה כעין סקילה, deavdia k'ein sekilah, you made
it like stoning it. אבל היכא דשחט בסכין, aval heicha deshachat besakin,
let's say you שחטת shachtat it with a knife, maybe that would
be like a completely different category. לא, and then you would say
that case actually it's not אסור. assur. If you actually שחטת shachtat
it and it wasn't even something that was similar to סקילה, sekilah,
maybe that actually would be totally permissible. So גמרא Gemara says no.
אמרי, אטו סכין כתיב באורייתא? atu sakin ketiv be'Oraita? What, you think
the תורה when it says שחיטה shechitah talks about a knife? דתנן,
Detnan, השוחט במגל יד בצור בקנה, hashochet bemagal yad b'tzur bekaneh, if
you שחט with like a hand scythe or a rock or a
reed, שחיטתו כשירה, shechitato kesherah, its שחיטה shechitah is kosher as long
as it's like a smooth non-nicked blade. So what does that mean?
It means the תורה doesn't recognize in the act of שחיטה shechitah
any difference between שחיטה shechitah with a knife or שחיטה shechitah with
a rock. Those have no different status in the world of שחיטה.
shechitah. And since they don't have any different status because the תורה
doesn't even identify the type of the knife, so if this פסוק
pasuk? means that some type of a שחיטה shechitah it remains forbidden,
that would be true by all types of שחיטה. shechitah. There's no
way you can distinguish between the types of שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, so
לא יאכל את בשרו tells me even if you made it like
beef, this applies once it's judged even if it has not been
stoned. And this tells me בעל השור נקי baal hashor naki that
you can't get הנאה. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. והשתא
דנפקא ליה איסור אכילה ואיסור הנאה מלא יאכל את בשרו. v'hashta denafka
leh issur achilah v'issur hanaah mi'lo yeachel et besaro. But one minute,
the גמרא Gemara says, but we just got through saying that once
לא יאכל is coming to tell me איסור אכילה, it will also
tell me איסור הנאה. Remember we just introduced that? So את בשרו
tells me that you שחטת shachtat it, this tells me you שחטת
shachtat it, שחיטה, shechitah, את בשרו, okay? So even if you שחטת
shachtat it, so now this tells me אכילה plus הנאה, right? Because
now we've established that לא יאכל includes an איסור הנאה. So if
you stone it, either you stone it and make it a נבילה,
neveilah, then you know it's אסור באכילה, assur beachilah,
or even if you made it like בשר basar and you שחטת
shachtat it, לא יאכל, you can't eat it or get הנאה. So
I don't need בעל השור נקי baal hashor naki to tell me
don't get הנאה anymore. So what am I going to do with
that part of the פסוק? pasuk. והשתא דנפקא ליה איסור אכילה ואיסור
הנאה מלא יאכל את בשרו בעל השור נקי למה לי? v'hashta denafka
leh issur achilah v'issur hanaah mi'lo yeachel et besaro baal hashor naki
lama li? להנאת עורו, lehanaat oro, to tell me you can't even
get benefit even from the skin. דסלקא דעתך אמינא... desalka daatach amina...
בשרו דאסור. Besaro deassur. Once you said בשרו, that sounds like the
problem is only in the meat of the
animal בהנאה, אבל עורו נשתרי בהנאה, aval oro nishrey behanaah, let me
actually, and that's actually worth a lot of money, right? You can
use it as leather and so on, maybe it's—so maybe it's limited
to בשרו. קמשמע לן בעל שור נקי. Kamashmalan baal shor naki. So
that's why it says נקי, you've been cleaned out, the same idea,
you don't get any benefit from it, not only no benefit from
the meat, you don't even get any benefit from the skin. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: והנך תנאי דמפקי ליה להאי
בעל שור נקי לדרשא אחריתא, Veehanach tanaei demafkei leh lehai baal shor
naki ledrasha achrita, כי דבעינן למימר לקמן, kidevainan lemeimar lekaman, the—the other
תנאים Tanaim that say בעל שור נקי baal shor naki teaches you
some—some other הלכה, halacha, parenthetically, as we're going to say later on—always
interesting when the גמרא Gemara is self-referential like that, whether that was
originally in the גמרא Gemara or whether that was glossed in later.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says we're going to say that בעל
שור נקי baal shor naki might mean something else, הנאת עורו מנלהו?
Hanas oro minlahu? Where do you learn out that you can't get
benefit from the skin? So you—so tell me here, after you've stoned
it, even if you שחט it, don't eat and don't get benefit.
So the only thing this is left to tell me is not
only from the meat, even from the skin. But if you use
this to tell me something else, where do I learn that you
can't get benefit from the—from the leather, from the skin? So the
גמרא Gemara says נפקא להו מ"את בשרו", nafkah lehu mi'et besaro, the
extra word of את, את הטפל לבשרו, Et hatafel lebesaro, not only
the meat itself, even the את בשרו, even the thing that is
secondary and connected, you know, appended to the meat, even the—even the
skin. מאי ניהו? Maineihu? What is it that's appended to the meat?
עורו, oro, the skin, the
leather. והאי תנא, Vehai tana, את why—so the other one who learns
from בעל שור נקי baal shor naki to speak about the skin,
why didn't he learn it from the word את? והאי תנא "את"
לא דריש, Vehai tana et lo darish, he doesn't דורש darshen את,
he doesn't think you can learn anything from the words את, and
this always gives us a fun opportunity to bring
in כדתניא, שמעון העמסוני ואמרי לה נחמיה העמסוני היה דורש כל אתין
שבתורה. kidtanya, Shimon HaAmsuni ve'amri leh Nechemiah HaAmsuni hayah doresh kol etin
shebaTorah. He would interpret all of the times it said את in
the תורה to come to say that's including something that is like
appended to, associated with the thing itself. כיוון שהגיע ל"את ה' אלוהיך
תירא", Kevan shehigia le'et Hashem Elokecha tira, but then he got to
the פסוק you should fear ה' Hashem your G-d, את, פירש, perish,
he separated. He said what can be comparable? What's seen
as—you know—what—what thing on this planet can be—can you—should you fear like
G-d? Could be like appended to G-d? אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru lo
talmidav, so his students said to him, רבי, כל אתין שדרשת מה
תהא עליהן? kol etin shedarashta mah tehei aleihen? What about all those
wonderful דרשות, drashot, everything you learned out from the time it said
את in the past? אמר להם, כשם שקיבלתי שכר על הדרישה, כך
קיבלתי שכר על הפרישה. Amar lahem, keshem shekibalti sachar al hadrisha, kach
kibalti sachar al haprisha. The same way I was rewarded by, like,
the, you know, learning out things from those words, כך קיבלתי שכר
על הפרישה. kach kibalti sachar al haprisha. I will get—you're getting שכר
sachar for your פרישה prisha right now, Rabbi Dave. I will get
שכר sachar for separating, for—for holding back. Which presumably—which is an amazing
statement, by the way, of like intellectual honesty. Like, I'm going to
give up, like, 20 years of my life's work because I realized
it was all based on a false premise. Okay. So—עד שבא רבי
עקיבא ולימד, ad sheba Rabbi Akiva velimmed, until רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
came and taught "את ה' אלוהיך תירא" לרבות תלמידי חכמים et Hashem
Elokecha tira lerabbot talmidei chachamim to come to include תורה sages, they
are considered to be like G-d. Now the of course question is
like what, and you know, שמעון העמסוני Shimon HaAmsuni could not realize
that? So the—the beautiful, sort of, teaching I always heard was, until
you could see a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham that would be willing
to give up, you know, 20 years of their life's work for
their intellectual honesty, you didn't think that any—you know—no תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham could be compared to, like, this idea of יראת ה'. yiras
Hashem. But now you sort of can really appreciate, you know, what
that type of, you know, dedication to truth of תורה could be
like, and that could evoke a sense of יראה yira that could
be compared to—to G-d. Now, by the way, תוספות Tosafot makes an
interesting point. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says כיוון שהגיע
ל"את ה' אלוהיך תירא" פירש. kevan shehigia le'et Hashem Elokecha tira perish.
תוספות Tosafot says אף על גב דפרק קמא דקידושין דריש, af al
gav de'perek kama de'Kiddushin darish, נאמר "איש אמו ואביו תיראו" ונאמר "את
ה' אלוהיך תירא", ne'emar ish immo ve'aviv tira, vene'emar et Hashem Elokecha
tira, השוה הכתוב מורא אב ואם למורא שמים. hishvah hakatuv moras av
va'em lemoras shamayim. So the גמרא Gemara says—I mean, מר Mar does
it in other places, fear for—a parent is made—is—is analogous to fear
of G-d. It says את ה' אלוהיך תירא, et Hashem Elokecha tira,
איש אמו ואביו תיראו. ish immo ve'aviv tira. The פסוקים pesukim phrase
it in similar ways, you know, G-d gives you life, your parents
give you life and so on, so you see we make those
types of comparisons. תוספות Tosafot says no, לא הוי ניחא ליה למדרשיה
לאוקמי לאתיא יתירא. Lo havi nich leih lemidrasheih le'ukmei le'atya yiteira. So
תוספות Tosafot says yes, but the—that's just sort of saying this מצווה
mitzvah is analogous to that מצווה. mitzvah. It would not actually, תוספות—the
Tosafot way I'll read תוספות Tosafot is—it's different to say something is
made analogous, it's another to say that in the מצווה mitzvah of
loving G-d, there's something that's associated with G-d that you're also supposed
to love, that's part of the מצווה mitzvah of loving G-d. Like,
that's actually making it too much in the same category, right? It's
very different to say there's a מצווה mitzvah to love G-d, a
מצווה mitzvah to love your parents, and there's some analogy between those
two מצוות, mitzvos, than to say the מצווה mitzvah to love G-d
includes the following people who are like G-d, right? That's, like, way
too close to possibly heretical, and that's what you're not prepared to
say. Okay, so—anyways, but then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, you
know what? Some תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim could be in that category.
How are we supposed to imagine that the גמרא Gemara, reconciled this
with the idea of מסורה masora and all these דרשות drashas are
passed down from Mount Sinai?
We don't assume that all the דרשות drashas are passed down from
Mount Sinai. The only thing we assume that about primarily is גזירה
שוה. gzera shava. And even by גזירה שוה, gzera shava, right? I
mean, you know, according to the Rambam, the Rambam assumes that the
whole reason that you have debates in the גמרא, Gemara the whole
basis of Karaitic critique of Rabbinic Judaism was you can't have real
you can't say you have authentic traditions; every single page you're arguing
about it, so obviously the transmission was broken and you can't trust
anything. And Rambam's basic response to that was was that very little
like this whole approach about like the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai was actually the content of it was passed down. And his
claim was that there was never debate about. All the rest is
just us using our human intellect to derive the הלכות halachos using
the hermeneutic principles. And therefore, that's why there are debates. So really
like nothing was passed down; it was all derived. Now, the problem
is that we say that גזירה שוה gzera shava has to have
been passed down. But as the Ramban already points out, a number
of גמרות Gemaros say, "Well, why do you make a גזירה שוה
gzera shava from this פסוק? Make it from that פסוק." And then
what's the question? A גזירה שוה gzera shava is total מסורה. masora.
Ramban says even a גזירה שוה gzera shava isn't total מסורה. masora.
מסורה masora is you can learn this הלכה halacha from a גזירה
שוה, gzera shava, but then you have like a lot of latitude
about like figure out what the גזירה שוה gzera shava is. So
the bottom line is very little, at least according to, you know,
I think the certainly from a modern perspective and according to the
Rambam and the and whatever and other ראשונים, Rishonim, very little is
actual that the content was handed down. You know, it's the ability
to דרשן darshan which is the empowering of like the empowering of
the Supreme Court. You empower the Rabbis to דרשן darshan and then
that becomes דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, right? So okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: תנו רבנן "ובעל השור נקי". רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר
omer "נקי מחצי כופר". naki michatzi kofer. Now we're going to say
the other things that you could learn out from "ובעל השור נקי".
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you don't have to pay חצי כופר.
chatzi kofer. If it were a תם, tam, so, you know, maybe
we should make an analogy. You pay כופר kofer by a מועד,
muad, full כופר; kofer; maybe a תם tam should pay half כופר.
kofer. Of course, again, פשט of the פסוקים psukim "ובעל השור נקי"
is exactly to tell you you don't have liability, but we, you
know, I maybe actually that's a דרשה drasha that fits. You're נקי
because and you're total נקי in the first three times as you're
not paying half כופר. kofer. But anyway, okay, "ובעל השור נקי", רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר "נקי מחצי כופר". naki michatzi kofer. Don't make
that analogy, you don't pay half כופר. kofer. אמר ליה רבי עקיבא,
Amar lei Rabbi Akiva, "והלא הוא עצמו אין משתלם אלא מגופו". V'halo
hu atzmo ein mishtalem ela migufo. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, "Well,
who needs that דרשה? drasha? You know, half payment, if you were
to make an analogy of a תם tam and half payment, half
payment of a תם tam is done from the animal itself. So
how could I pay half כופר? kofer? יבאו לבית דין ויסלקו לך.
Yavou l'veit din v'yisalku lach. Let the owner say, 'Oh, you want
to get your half כופר kofer payment from my ox? Be my
guest! After we stone it, we'll bring it to בית דין beit
din and you can get paid from it.' And we've just found
out that you can't get any benefit from it at all. So
who needs to say you don't pay half כופר kofer because you
would make an analogy to a שור תם? shor tam? If you
make that analogy, you'd get paid from the body of the ox,
but the body of the ox isn't worth anything because you're stoning
it, right? Is that clear? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, who
needs that דרשה? drasha? Even if the הלכה halacha would be you
should pay half כופר, kofer, there'd be nothing to pay because the
body would be would be worthless. People with me? I'm getting these
blank looks. Do you understand the point? Okay, fine. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says, "Okay, יבאו לבית דין ויסלקו לך." Yavou l'veit
din v'yisalku lach. So אמר ליה רבי אליעזר, Amar lei Rabbi Eliezer,
so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said back to him, "כך אני בעיניך?
Kach ani b'einecha? That's what you think of me? שדנתי בזה? Shedanti
b'zeh? I
gotta love it. That you think I would be talking about a
case like that where they actually stone the ox? Of course if
they stone the ox, there's no way to get payment." אמר לו,
Amar lo, שחייב מיתה? shechayav mita? No. אין דיני, Ein dini, my
the דין din I was dealing with was אלא כשהעמידו את האדם
על פי עד אחד או על פי בעלים, ela k'shehe'emidu et ha'adam
al pi ed echad o al pi be'alim, that we don't we're
not going to stone the ox, that you need two witnesses to
stone the ox. So here the owner admitted or one witness admitted
or said that it had been, that would not be enough to
stone the ox, that's like a murder trial, you need two, but
maybe certainly your own admission, maybe that would be enough that you
should be paying כופר kofer and half כופר. kofer. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara. says, "Wait one minute. על פי בעלים, Al pi be'alim,
מודה בקנס הוא. Modeh b'knas hu. One minute, if the owners are
admitting, you wouldn't pay based on that, you're admitting to a קנס.
knas. No, קסבר כופר כפרה. Kasvar kofer kapara. No, כופר kofer is
a כפרה, kapara, so it's like admitting that you're חייב chayav a
קרבן. korban. If you admit you're חייב chayav a קרבן, korban, you
admit you're חייב כפרה, chayav kapara, you admit you're חייב, chayav, so
there's no two witnesses, we're not going to stone the ox, you
admit and we would make you pay based on your own admission
because it's a כפרה, kapara, it's not a קנס." knas. Okay, תניא
אידך, Tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא. braisa. אמר לו רבי אליעזר,
Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said to back to
him when after רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said "How you're supposed to
be paying כופר kofer from a stoned ox?" "עקיבא, כך אני בעיניך
שדנתי בזה? Akiva, kach ani b'einecha shedanti b'zeh?
That's what you think of me? That you think I'd be dealing
with a case that they stoned the ox? שחייב מיתה? Shechayav mita?
That I'm dealing with a case that the ox was was worthy
of being stoned? אין דיני אלא במתכוין להרוג את הבהמה והרג את
האדם. Ein dini ela b'mitkavein laharog et habeheima v'harag et ha'adam. I'm
talking about a case where the ox isn't going to be stoned,
but you..." Still pay a כופר. kofer. What would be that? Remember
I asked you earlier this morning to think about when you might
have not stoning the ox, but still paying כופר? kofer? Right? About
the stadium ox. Could it be you don't stone it, it's not
wicked enough, it's not a murder enough to be stoned, but you
would pay a כופר. kofer. So he says, let's say the ox
tried to kill an animal and accidentally killed a person. Okay, almost
would be like maybe a רגל regel case or a שן shein
case too, going back to that. So it's not trying to kill
a person, it's not murder, so you're not going to stone it,
but a person died as a result, so you would pay כופר.
kofer. All right, שנתכוין להרוג את הבהמה והרג את האדם sheniskaven laharog
et habeheima veharag et haadam or למצרי le'mitzri again really meaning לגוי
legoy והרג ישראל, veharag yisrael, okay, where you won't stone it, but
because it did not do, you know, this act that's worthy of
stoning, but a human life was lost. לנפלים linefalim or tried to
kill a fetus, which is not, again, would not be an act
of murder if a person did that, והרג בן קיימא veharag ben
kayama and killed a viable person. So therefore it would be a
case where it intentionally took a where it did not do an
act of trying to kill a human life or whatever to take
a life that would be חייב מיתה, hayav misa, but nevertheless a
life was lost, so it won't get סקילה sekila but it will
be כופר. kofer. And again, this would be good evidence, by the
way, that in the case of like רגל, regel, like it would
be parallel to this, right, if you say that there's כופר kofer
by רגל. regel. No סקילה sekila because it wasn't trying to take
a life, it wasn't this כוונה להזיק kavana lehazik and so on,
but nevertheless a life was lost, so there could be כופר. kofer.
Here though it's even worse, it is a כוונה להזיק, kavana lehazik,
it's got a כוונה להזיק kavana lehazik to kill a human being
or to kill a whatever, a person that you'd be חייב מיתה
hayav misa for. So let's just do one more line in the
גמרא. האי אמר להו ברישא. hai amar lehu bereisha. Which one of
these two answers did he say first? רב כהנא משמיה דרבה אמר
נתכוין אמר להו ברישא. Rav Kahana mishmei d'Rava amar niskaven amar lehu
bereisha. First he gave the answer of trying to kill an animal
and killed a human. רב טביומי משמיה דרבה אמר הן מתו אמר
להו ברישא. Rav Tavyumi mishmei d'Rava amar hen meisu amar lehu bereisha.
No, first he gave the answer about trying to kill through the
that it was the person's own testimony, and that's why we know
that it killed but we don't have witnesses that it killed. So
רב כהנא משמיה דרבה אמר נתכוין אמר להו ברישא. Rav Kahana mishmei
d'Rava amar niskaven amar lehu bereisha. משל לצייד ששולה דגים מן הים.
mashal letzayad sheshola dagim min hayam. Like somebody who is capturing fish
and taking them out of the sea. משכח רברבי, mishkach ravrevei, so
first he gets some nice big fish, שקיל, shakil, he takes it.
That's great, I got a big catch. זוטרי, zutrei, then afterwards he
gets small little fish afterwards, you know what, שקיל, shakil, I'm not
going to throw them back, I'm going to keep those too. So
first he has the good answer. We're assuming the better answer is
נתכוין להרוג את הבהמה והרג את האדם, niskaven laharog et habeheima veharag
et haadam, because that's the type of a case where the animal
was fundamentally not חייב מיתה. hayav misa. It's not just it lacked
the right type of testimony and witnesses, fundamentally it's not חייב מיתה.
hayav misa. So that's the big fish, that's the better answer. So
first he gave a good answer to Rabbi Akiva and then he
said, oh, you know what, I thought of another supporting answer. It's
not as good as my real answer. Here's my real answer, but
here's another case too. You'll keep the small fish. רב טביומי משמיה
דרבה אמר הן מתו אמר להו ברישא. Rav Tavyumi mishmei d'Rava amar
hen meisu amar lehu bereisha. No, first he said the weaker answer.
משל לצייד ששולה דגים מן הים, mashal letzayad sheshola dagim min hayam,
you're catching fish, משכח זוטרי שקיל, mishkach zutrei shakil, you find a
small fish, you keep it. You don't know if you're going to
get a big fish. משכח רברבי, mishkach ravrevei, then you get the
big fish, שדי זוטרי, shadi zutrei, you throw out the small fish.
Who needs the small fish anymore? ושקיל רברבי, ve'shakil ravrevei, you keep
the big one. So first he gave a weaker answer, then he
realized he had a better answer, so forget the first answer I
gave, I'll give you a better answer. Okay? So it's an interesting,
interesting, what? That obviously does make more sense. Okay, we will continue
with this tomorrow.
Rabbi, a bullfighter was killed the other day.
Really? A bullfighter was killed the other day? Just the other day.
It was in the news.
Wow, look at that. It must have been...